{
  "reference_number": "12552",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "We need the most ambitious change. We cannot exclude agriculture, we cannot rely on Carbon Emission Trading Schemes and we\n cannot exclude some gasses and include others. So called short lived gasses can nevertheless have long term effects. Even if the\n goverment fails/ refuses to do the above, it should set a target of net zero long-lived gases by 2050 and mandate the Climate\n\n Commission to recommend or set a 2050 target for so called short-lived gases."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We should be cutting emissions here (including by planting more forests) in New Zealand and not by buying overseas credits. Zero\n should mean zero. We cannot \"contract out\" of domestic change."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The 2050 target should not be able to be weakened, but only strengthened. There shoud be 'no backsliding'."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. Emissions budgets under the Zero Carbon Act should cover five year periods and be set three budgets in advance. This will\n provide long-term certainty."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Budgets should only be changed due to very significant changes in scientific understanding, not political or economic developments.\n\n The target and budget should be allowed to be streghtened but not wakened, and there should not be any relience on carbon\n trading schemes or ignoring of some contributory gasses."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Only strenghten, see previous comments."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, I agree that they will need to consider: - scientific knowledge regarding climate change - technology relevant to climate change -\nsocial circumstances and the likely impact of a decision on fuel poverty - energy policy and the likely impact of a decision on energy\n\nsupplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy - economic circumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the\neconomy, as well as the competitiveness of particular sectors of the economy - fiscal circumstances and the likely impact of the\ndecision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing. There should be strong considetation and expertise on poverty and\n\nsocial security with the ability to recomend that any negative effects be mitigated via public social security spending."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "In setting plans to meet the emissions budgets, the government should be: - making sure they're based on the best science\navailable - ensuring that they deliver fair outcomes for Kiwis - reflecting the principle of a Just Transition for workers - honouring Te Tiriti\n\no Waitangi - being environmentally sustainable, especially for New Zealand's unique native plants and animals - maximising the impact\nof money spent and being cost-effective - encouraging innovation - unlocking economic opportunities for New Zealanders, such as in\n\nrenewable energy - honouring our international commitments, including under the Paris Agreement - consulting people who may be\neconomically affected, like farmers or businesses - consulting tangata whenua - consulting young people, who'll live to see more of\n\nthe impact of climate change - consulting communities already facing the physical impacts of climate change"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Such schemes should not be used in reaching our 2050 target. Neverthelesss, if they are to be used, the Commission should advise\n\nthe government on policy around the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree that members of the Climate Commission should have expertise in: - climate and environmental science including mātauranga\nMāori - climate change policy (including emissions trading) - te Tiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori (Māori language, culture,\nand philosophy) and Māori interests - knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system - risk\n\nmanagement - resource economics and impacts (including labour markets and distribution) - experience with addressing adaptation\nchallenges like planning, insurance and local government - engineering and/or infrastructure - community engagement and\n\ncommunications - business competitiveness In addition, they should have expertise in: - expertise in public health - understanding of\nour international commitments, including under the Paris Agreement - understanding of the social impacts of climate change and/or\n\ngovernment policy - knowledge of principles of equity and a Just Transition -knowledge of povery and work The commission should\ninclude someone whith specific and dedicated expertise on social consequences including ensuring social security for all Kiwis and\n\nsecurity of work. This roles should not be subsumed into a role driven by business interests and economics."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There should be be a separate adaptation sub-committee of the Commission, as in the UK."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes, the Zero Carbon Act should require: - a national climate change risk assessment - a national adaptation plan - regular reviews of\n\nprogress towards implementing the national adaptation plan - an adaptation reporting power Care will need to be taken in managing\nthe interaction between national and local government roles."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. This would let the government and the public know about the risks to public and other infrastructure, and make these\n\norganisations better informed about the risks they face."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We shouold also be assisting other contries including Pacific Contries deal with Climate Change."
    }
  ]
}
